Today, I'm interviewing Reiner
Pope, who is the CEO of MatX,
which is a new chip startup.
Previously, he was doing TPU architecture
and many other things at Google.
This is a very different format
from my usual interviews.
This is going to be a blackboard lecture.
We're going to get up in a second.
We in fact built this whole new
studio with specifically this
format in mind, so it's a pleasure
to get to inaugurate it with you.
We're going to be talking
about model architecture, ML
infra, and many other things.
The reason I think it's an important
topic is because once you understand how
training and inference work in a cluster,
a lot of things—about why AI is the way
it is, why AI architectures are the way
they are, why API prices are the way they
are, and fundamentally why AI progress
is the way it is—start making sense.
You need to understand the details
to get there, and you need a
blackboard to understand the details.
Reiner, thank you so much for doing this.
Very happy to be here.
Full disclosure, I am an angel
investor in MatX, but that's
unrelated to this podcast.
Reiner, to kick us off
I'll ask this question.
We have a couple of companies
like Claude and Codex and Cursor
offering something like Fast Mode,
where for 6x the price, they'll
stream you tokens at 2.5x the speed.
Mechanically, I'm curious
what's going on here.
Why is it the case that you can
pay more to get faster latency?
Two, could you keep going?
Could you pay 100x more and
somehow get much faster speeds?
Three, could you go the other way?
Could you have something like Claude
Code "Slow Mode", where if you are
willing to wait for minutes on end,
you could get even cheaper prices?
Maybe this will help motivate the analysis
that you'll be doing through the lecture.
Great.
To jump to the conclusion a little
bit, the big effect is batch size.
What we're going to do now is quantify
exactly what that looks like and what
its implications are on latency and cost.
There's another effect, which
you can call speculative decoding
or multi-token prediction.
We can maybe come back to that
later, but the first thing that
we'll talk through is batch size.
What I'd like to introduce is
the two principles of analysis.
First, we're going to look at a
roofline analysis of how we run a
transformer model on a cluster of chips.
We'll take a
Blackwell NVL72 cluster,
so a rack of 72 GPUs.
The roofline analysis means we look at
memory bandwidth and compute performance.
The other side of that is that we're
going to look at just two simple
factors of the model: the time to
operate on the weights, and the time to
operate on the context, the KV cache.
Let's jump in.
We're going to try and estimate
the time that it takes to run
an inference of a certain shape.
We're not perfect here.
We can't exactly predict the time, so
instead we're going to approximate.
We're going to say that the
time must be greater than or
equal to a certain quantity.
We're going to consider two different
aspects: the time it takes to
do the memory fetches, and the
time it takes to do the compute.
It will turn out that this
gives us very strong predictive
power, even with a simple model.
One by one, what is the time
that it takes to do the compute?
There are really two things
I need to do in the compute.
I need to multiply by all of the
active parameters, and then I need
to do some work on the attention.
Multiplying by all the active parameters,
I have a certain batch size that
I'm running, and I've got a number
of active parameters in my model.
Then I'm just going to divide
this by the compute throughput,
which is the FLOPs of the chip.
This is a hardware concern.
This accounts for all of the compute time
for all of the weight matrix multiplies.
There's a little caveat here.
We've ignored the time to do any of the
attention computation, but that in general
will be quite small in comparison to this.
So we'll ignore this.
I'll just interrupt from time to
time to ask some very naive questions
or to clarify some basic points.
For the audience, you're not
serving one user at a time.
The batch refers to the fact that you're
serving many different users at the
same time, and that's a whole batch.
I can motivate the batch
at least a little bit.
We will see exactly why batch is
such a favorable optimization.
What will turn out to be the case is
that if you do not batch together many
users, the cost and the economics you
get can be a thousand times worse than
if you do batch many users together.
We'll be able to see
that quite explicitly.
Then, number of active parameters.
If I look at, for example, a DeepSeek
model, the DeepSeek V3 model has
about 37 billion active parameters,
and 700 billion total parameters.
We're focusing on just the ones that
are active for a single AI token.
We're modeling compute performance.
I'm going to keep writing equals, but in
all of these cases, you can think of this
time as being at least this much, and
maybe there will be some terms we ignored.
On the memory side, what do
we need to do with memory?
We need to fetch all of the weights,
so there is some time to fetch
the total number of parameters,
not just the active parameters.
There's weight fetch time, and then in
addition, there's a KV cache fetch time.
This actually depends on batch size.
For every element of the batch,
we have to fetch an entire context
length worth of tokens, and
there's a size per token, bytes
for one token.
This is a model parameter.
Maybe just backing up, let's explain
what the KV cache is real quick.
When I do a forward pass… Let me draw
how the autoregressive inference works.
This is during decode.
If I have a bunch of text tokens… I'm
drawing a tensor because ultimately
the tokens are represented as
a tensor in some embedding dimension.
In this direction, I
have the sequence length.
The work of running a decode is that
I have to run each token through
a whole bunch of matrix multiplies
over a bunch of different layers.
In general, I'm going to have to do
that work over all of these tokens.
But one step of decode is to produce
just this one additional token up here.
What I'm going to do there is run a full
forward pass of multiplying by all of
the weight matrices in the entire model.
But then I've got this attention
mechanism where this token is looking
at all of the past tokens, and
what is it looking at specifically?
It is looking at some internal
representation that the model
has produced of the tokens,
and we call that the KV cache.
This process of this single
token attending to all of the
history of tokens is attention.
It is mostly dominated by memory
fetches rather than matrix multiplies.
So we've got the amount of memory
that we're fetching shown over here,
and then this is of course just
divided by the memory bandwidth,
so the memory bytes per second.
In fact, these equations here are enough
for us to now draw some fit lines.
The things that we'd like to look at
are sensitivity to batch, and then also,
which we'll draw separately, to context
length.
We said that the big effect you
can get is some trade-off in
latency versus cost in batch size.
Let's draw them out.
I think there are just really
two graphs that we want to draw.
We'll first draw batch
size versus time here.
When we look at the shape of
this, we've got a maximum of
the sum and then another term.
Let's look at these terms one by one
and how they scale: the time for compute
and memory, and how they show up.
Let's first look at this compute time.
This is just purely linear in
batch size with no offset, so
it is some curve like this.
This is t compute.
On the memory side, we've got some
portion here that is just this constant
in some base offset here,
which is the weight fetch.
Finally, we have this term here,
which is the KV fetch, which is pretty
linear in batch size, and
so it looks like that.
The sum of this plus this maxed with
this… Let's at least first draw the sum.
The two memory times in conjunction end
up looking on this curved slope like this.
Then the overall maximum is—I'll
draw a little thicker here—the
maximum of these two curves.
What does this mean?
This is a latency plot.
If I grow my batch size, initially I
get some not very strong dependence
on batch size, so there is some
lower bound on latency here.
This already partially
answers the question.
For a given hardware configuration—and
we can talk about varying the hardware
configuration—there is a
lower bound on latency.
It is simply that I need to
read all of my total parameters
from memory into the chips, and
that takes a certain amount of time.
If I use all of my memory bandwidth,
I can't do any better than that.
It seems like the way you've drawn
the slopes for compute time and how
the KV grows—and what implication
the KV has on memory time—
What if
this were above or below?
Yeah, is that necessarily the case?
If this is always true, then as
batch size grows compute always
dominates KV, which suggests that
if you have a big enough batch size,
maybe memory is never an issue.
This is really sensitive to the
context length, so I think we
should come back and explore this.
As you vary the context length, the
KV fetch time will go up and up, and
that will cause a transition from
compute-limited to memory-limited.
Is there something especially
significant about the slope being
exactly the slope of the compute time?
Whenever we have balance points, it says
that you're getting it exactly right.
For the particular context length
where the slopes match, that says I am
equally memory-bound and compute-bound,
which is a really desirable place to
be.
This is a very simple algebra problem,
but suppose the optimal is 100K context
length, and you go to 200K context length.
Does your MFU go down to 50%?
Does it have a humongous impact on MFU
to be slightly outside of the optimal
context length range, the Goldilocks zone?
That's right.
That is true as modeled here.
There is a key point here that
I'm modeling the memory fetch
as linear in context length.
That depends on model architecture.
It is true for all of the model
architectures with dense attention.
Sparse attention actually
scales much better than that.
Got it.
Is sparse attention what
everybody uses in practice?
I'm pretty excited about sparse attention.
It's hard to know what the labs are using.
DeepSeek has published a
sparse attention mechanism.
I'll just put a plug in that some
of the DeepSeek papers that have
published sparse attention end up
putting a square root in this term.
So far, we've looked at the latency.
It's hard to read off cost from this.
If I think about what cost means…
To run this inference, I'm going to use
the GPU for a certain number of seconds,
like one millisecond or 20 milliseconds.
I have to pay the rental
time for that time.
So it's $2/hour per GPU
or something like that.
That's the cost of this inference,
but how many tokens have I
processed during that inference?
That is the batch size.
What we actually want to plot is
the cost versus batch size, which
is t over B versus batch size.
This is the cost per token.
We have to imagine dividing each
of these three curves by B, so
multiplying by this reciprocal.
What we end up with there
is… The compute curve
was linear.
We divide by B, and that
makes it a constant here.
This is t compute.
The KV fetch was linear, and now
it becomes a constant as well.
Then the weight fetch
was constant, and now we've
divided by B, so it becomes this
parabola.
Again, we're going to
compute the max of the sum.
The sum of these two terms
shifts the parabola up.
The sum of the KV fetch and
the weight fetch gives us
a higher parabola that's like this.
Then we're going to take
the max with the compute
here.
We end up with this being the
overall shape that we care about.
Again, we see some limiting behavior.
The cost initially starts very
high at a batch size of one.
It almost goes to infinity because we've
got so many weight fetches that are
not amortized over a large batch size.
But as we increase the batch size, the
weight fetches become amortized over so
many different batch elements that their
cost grows very small, and eventually the
compute time ends up driving the cost.
So there is a limiting
lower bound on cost,
which is this line here.
So Claude Code Slow or Codex Slow or
whatever would just live on this line.
It wouldn't help much because
you're not able to amortize the KV
values over a much bigger batch.
They're unique per batch.
The compute is also unique per batch.
So what is the minimum work
you can do per batch after
amortizing everything else away?
This point where you are no longer
memory bandwidth bound, practically
how big a batch do you need?
How big are the batches
practically for frontier models?
You can just solve for that.
It's not even particularly
sensitive to model architecture.
Let's go ahead and do that.
What we're talking about is when the
memory time is equal to the compute time.
That’s what that question is.
Because we're focused on what the batch
size is—and really there's a question
of when the weights are amortized
over the multiplies—I'm going to
focus on comparing the weight fetch
time to the weight multiply time.
I'm going to disregard the KV fetch
term just to simplify the analysis
so we can get a clean answer out.
We're going to equate
this portion with these two times.
Writing that out, we get N,
number of total parameters,
over memory bandwidth,
is equal to
batch size times number
of active parameters
divided by the compute performance.
Looking over here, everything
on the top are model parameters.
Everything on the bottom
are hardware parameters.
It turns out to be nice to
rearrange them such that we have
the hardware parameters on one side.
This is equivalent to
FLOPs over memory bandwidth
being equal to batch size times
number of active parameters,
divided by the number of total parameters.
This hardware
parameter ends up being
a dimensionless constant.
If you look in terms of FLOPs…
What are the dimensions of this?
This is multiplies per second.
This is bytes per second.
So that's not quite dimensionless.
But what you do is you say, how
many FP4 multiplies per second times
the fact that each FP4 is half a byte.
I can actually make this
end up being dimensionless.
On most GPUs, this ends up being
somewhere around 300.
Has that ratio changed over
time as we've gone from model
generation to model generation,
where the FLOPs keep increasing?
This is a hardware parameter.
To what extent has the hardware changed?
From A100 to H100 to B100, the
FLOPs have increased substantially,
the memory bandwidth has also
increased substantially, and it
has remained reasonably stable.
We can express this one as well.
This is a sparsity parameter.
I might even phrase this
slightly differently.
Let's solve for batch size in total.
Moving this back over to the other
side, we end up with batch size needs
to be bigger than approximately 300
times sparsity.
For example, in DeepSeek I activate 32
out of 256 experts, so this
would be 8 for DeepSeek.
This actually gives you a ballpark which
is remarkably accurate to practice.
Generally, people will go a
little bit larger than this.
They don't really want to be
exactly at the balance point because
real-world efficiencies aren't as
good as a roofline analysis would say.
But take this and maybe
double or triple it.
Okay, so it's two to three
thousand tokens per batch.
But then if you included the KV
cache, the implication would be
that the optimal batch size...
Should grow larger.
We solved for the equivalence between
when compute time is equal to memory time.
If I add in something that consumes
more memory bandwidth, then I have
less available for the weight loads.
I need to grow the memory bandwidth
more, and therefore the batch size more.
This seems incredibly small.
This would be less than
one sequence, right?
Keep in mind that I'm talking
about the number of tokens that
I'm generating one more token for.
It's actually 2,000 unique sequences.
Got it.
We're just talking about a single
forward pass on these sequences.
You think of the batch as
the number of sequences.
That’s right.
When I'm prepping for interviews, I
often talk to experts in the field.
So for Reiner, I chatted with two of
Jane Street's engineers, Clark and Axel.
Clark, who works on low latency trading
systems, walked me through why Jane
Street uses FPGAs to make sure that they
have predictable nanosecond latencies.
“You can just build these like giant
grids of compute very easily that do
exactly what you need that touch a
hundred megabytes of SRAM and then
get your response back in tens of
nanoseconds very easily. And that's
basically impossible on a CPU.”
He then went on to explain why CPUs just
wouldn't work for this kind of thing.
“And so if you have a clock that's going
every three nanoseconds, you actually
have several bytes of information
at a time to make your decision.
That's as opposed to a CPU where you'll
just collect up a whole packet, you
know, let's say a 1500-byte packet, and
then you say, okay, this packet's ready.
Here you go, CPU.
You can start thinking about it now.”
FPGAs allow you to react to the earliest
part of the packet as it arrives, rather
than having to wait for the full thing.
We also talked about liquid cooling,
network design, and many other things.
If you're interested in this
stuff, Jane Street is hiring.
You can check out their open
roles at JaneStreet.com/Dwarkesh.
And if you want to watch the full prep
conversation, we posted it there too.
If you've got a frontier model and you are
actually doing inference, surely they must
have more than 2,000 concurrent users.
Is there any added latency
from the fact that you need to
have the whole batch fill up?
Or if you have a reasonable amount
of users, is it so unlikely that
it would take you 100 milliseconds
to fill up the next 2,000 slots?
The way to think about this is: when
does the train depart, as a model?
Let's say I've picked a batch
size that I'm going to run at.
By the way, this intersection point
is the same intersection point here.
I pick this batch size, and I
know that it's going to take, for
example, 20 milliseconds, which is
a common place this ends up landing.
This is a timeline of what
is running on the GPU.
It's going to start a new batch
every 20 milliseconds regardless.
You can think of this as
a schedule for the train.
A new train departs every 20 milliseconds.
Any passengers who are
ready board the train.
If the train is full, they
wait until the next train.
If the train is not full, the
train is going to go anyway.
In terms of what that means for queuing
latency, the worst case is that a request
arrives just after the train departed.
It has to wait for the next train, so
that's up to 20 milliseconds, and then it
has to wait for that train to complete.
So the worst-case latency
is 40 milliseconds.
How is the 20 milliseconds derived?
It's a rule of thumb, but where it
comes from is not fully explained yet.
So far we've focused on memory
bandwidth and compute time.
When we look at memory, the other
consideration is that we want to use
all of the memory capacity we have.
Generally, we're going to use
all of that memory capacity to
store the weights or the KVs.
In the time of doing a forward
pass, we want to read all of the
memory capacity into the chip.
That is capacity divided by bandwidth.
That tends to be 20 milliseconds on
many different generations of HBM.
The units make sense.
You would have
a byte divided by bytes per second.
For example, on the Rubin generation,
it is something like 288 gigabytes
divided by 20 terabytes per second.
This
comes out to about 15
milliseconds.
Let me make sure I understand
what this is saying.
I understand the unit analysis.
What it's saying is
we can evacuate and replace
the HBM in this amount of time.
So we don't want to be in a situation
where the HBM is not big enough that we're
not actually able to write everything we
want to it or take everything out of it.
Or we don't want to be in a situation
where our ability to write back
and forth is so small compared...
There are sort of two scenarios.
Why don't we pick a latency that
is bigger than 15 milliseconds?
If I think about what that
means, it means I actually have
time to read the HBM twice.
By the way, most HBM accesses
are reads, not writes.
It's almost all reads because the
weight matrices are read-only, and
almost all of the KV cache accesses
are reads.
In around 30 milliseconds,
I can read all of HBM twice,
but what's the point of that?
I don't want to read the
weight matrices twice.
I don't want to read the KVs twice.
Makes a ton of sense.
A couple of quick questions.
If it is the case that the optimal
batch size is something like 2,000,
it's totally dependent on the
sparsity, not dependent on
the model size or anything.
Sparsity shows up in model size,
but beyond that, it only depends
on sparsity, not on scale.
That's a very interesting result.
One question is how much of a push
towards centralization is it that
you would have these economies of
scale from inference for batching?
But it seems like it's
not that big a deal.
Is 2,000 users at the same time a lot?
It doesn't seem like a lot.
We can do a bit of analysis on this.
You can think of it in terms of number of
users, but a more productive way to think
of it is in terms of tokens per second.
What does this batch size
mean in terms of tokens
per second of the system?
Tokens per second is going to
be equal to the batch size.
We run a batch of tokens, and we do that
every time interval, which is
equal to the 15-millisecond
or 20-millisecond number.
This ends up being batch
size times about 60, so 64
x B.
This ends up being around 2,000 x
64, so 128,000 tokens per second.
This is in more digestible units.
It's hard to reason about
concurrent users, but what is
the global traffic for a system?
When you look at some of the
announcements, sometimes the
API providers will brag about
how much traffic they have.
The numbers I remember from some
announcements of Gemini last year
were in the hundreds of millions
of tokens per second worldwide.
This
is one-thousandth of that.
Gemini is big.
One-thousandth of Gemini is a lot.
To actually be competitive at scale,
you need to be able to serve at
least one-thousandth of Gemini.
That's interesting.
The more sparsity you have,
the less compute you need.
It does seem that as batch sizes get
bigger, compute ends up being the
bottleneck, according to this analysis.
Then the question is, how
far can you take sparsity?
As the sparsity ratio increases, as you
have fewer active parameters relative
to total parameters, how much is the
performance of the model degrading?
Is it degrading faster than you're saving
compute by increasing the sparsity factor?
You mean the quality of the model,
rather than the speed of the model.
Unfortunately, we're not able
to answer that analytically.
That is an empirical
question of model quality.
The best I can do is pull up a
paper and answer that empirically.
Should
we pull up the paper now?
This paper is "Unified Scaling
Laws for Routed Language Models."
It's a somewhat old paper by this
stage, but one of the things they looked
at is if I keep increasing sparsity,
what is the model quality impact?
This answer is very sensitive to the
actual choice of mixture of experts.
Mixture of experts has been around for a
really long time, maybe even back in 2017,
but the techniques have changed a lot.
DeepSeek's mixture of experts was
a big change in how it worked.
There have been older papers, like
"GShard" and "Switch Transformer".
The actual empirical results are
going to depend on all of that.
On one of the older techniques shown
here, you can see if I hold constant
the number of active parameters at
a certain size, and then I increase
the sparsity, which they call expert
count, the quality keeps increasing.
If you imagine drawing a horizontal
line from 1.3B dense across, you end up
seeing that, in this case, the 64-expert
370-million activated parameter model
is as good as a dense 1.3-billion model.
So in some sense, it's actually
not amazing returns where you need
to increase total parameters a
hundredfold to get the equivalent
of 10x as many active parameters.
Actually even more so.
It's a huge increase in parameter count
for a modest increase in efficiency.
So in this case, actually it's 4x?
64x for 4x.
So while it is true that you get this
benefit of being able to economize
on your compute time if you increase
sparsity, naively it would seem
like a trade-off worth making.
But if you're decreasing
this by 2x and then having this go up
by 8x every time you double sparsity...
Is that good or bad, actually?
Even from a memory point of view…
Keep in mind you are doubling this
portion of the memory fetches,
which is amortized by batch.
So just keep running a larger batch size.
From the point of view of the analysis
we've done here, this is a pure win.
Keep doing it until you run out
of available users, basically.
There's
this equivalence where if I have a lot of
users, I can go to a much sparser model.
From that point of view,
it's a reasonable trade-off.
The other trade-off that shows up here
is that it also consumes memory capacity.
We've only reasoned about
memory bandwidth here, but it
also consumes memory capacity.
I see.
Let me make sure I understood.
You're saying we want
to spend less time computing,
therefore we do more sparsity.
To make that work, we
need bigger batch sizes.
Which means we need more memory capacity
to have more sparsity.
Maybe this would be a good point to talk
about how a mixture of experts layer is
typically laid out on a rack of GPUs.
Cool.
Makes sense.
Where were we?
Sparse mixture of experts.
Maybe how we lay that out on a GPU.
Let's zoom in on the mixture of experts
layer first and draw what that looks like.
Typically, we'll have some kind of
a router layer, which is making the
decision of where we route the tokens to.
We get tokens coming in here, they
go through a router layer, and then
we have a bunch of different experts.
I'll draw a few more to line some up.
The router will make a decision
of which experts it's going to
route to, and it will be a small
fraction of them, maybe 1 in 32.
Maybe it will make a decision
to route to this one,
maybe this one, and maybe this one.
Each expert itself is a normal MLP.
It has an up projection and then a down
projection with a nonlinearity in between.
Then finally, we do the inverse operation.
Where we were broadcasting things
out here, we're going to bring
them back in and sum them up.
Bringing them in like
this.
Then finally, we have
our residual connections.
The token is also passed through
here, and it gets added to
the result of the MoE layer.
This is a normal MoE layer.
What I want to talk through is how
this is mapped to a GPU rack and what
this means for communication, because
I think this will start to show some
of the limits of how sparse we can go.
The standard practice here,
and it is the best solution,
is to use expert parallelism.
That means different experts
go on different GPUs.
If we take something like a DeepSeek
model, they have 256 experts.
Let's say we want to run
that on a Blackwell rack.
There are 72 GPUs.
We have a divisibility problem.
This is not a power of two.
We'll just simplify and say we're
only going to use 64 of them.
Just ignore the other eight.
It's not a big deal.
So we have four experts per GPU.
Very simple.
For the sake of the diagram,
actually let's just say we
have two experts per GPU.
We end up just putting
these GPU boundaries.
Every pair of experts is on its own GPU.
Then we can look at
the communication cost.
We had some tokens stored centrally here.
They get routed to all of these experts,
and there is some
communication cost paid here.
There's the same communication
cost paid on the output.
The hope is that this does not
become communication limited.
Now
what is the traffic pattern here?
The traffic pattern here is
that any GPU will be talking to
any other GPU, depending on the
decisions made by the model.
This is an all-to-all traffic pattern.
When you say any GPU in the pre-tense,
the router is more than one GPU?
I drew this as one router.
In reality, you would actually have
many copies of the router, and you would
have as many routers as GPUs, in fact.
As the incoming traffic.
Yeah.
These are 64 GPUs and these are 64 GPUs.
It's actually the same GPUs, we
just draw them as separate because
they're serving different purposes.
So at this point, any GPU can
be sending to any other GPU.
This all-to-all pattern of communication
that shows up and how the Blackwell
racks are configured is a perfect fit for
the communication pattern that the MoE
actually wants to do.
However, if you think maybe one rack
is too slow and I want to do two
racks, then I have this challenge
that maybe I've got some sort of rack
boundary drawn outside here like this,
and I no longer have all-to-all
communication between all
the GPUs in two racks.
The rack-to-rack communication ends
up being a substantial bottleneck.
The fundamental thing here is
that one rack bounds the size
of an expert layer you can do.
This has been part of what's
been driving towards larger and
larger interconnect domains.
Before we continue, it may be worth
you explaining what exactly a rack is.
The differences in bandwidth between
a rack and within a rack, and the
all-to-all versus not all-to-all nature
of communication within versus outside.
This is a place where it starts to be very
different between Nvidia, for example,
and Google, and then others, including us.
Generally, a rack
is a physical structure.
It's a few meters tall, a meter or
two wide, depending on configuration,
and it stores some number of GPUs
or XPUs, which is typically about
64.
What constrains it being a
certain size is power delivery,
weight, and cooling ability.
It ends up being about this
size in many cases because of
these physical constraints.
When I deploy a data center, a data
center may have thousands of these racks.
I've got one of these tall racks, it's
got a bunch of GPUs in it, and so on.
And then I put another rack next to it.
You make it sound so easy.
Right.
I just drop them in.
In Nvidia's case, the
communication topology…
They actually put the GPUs on the
outside of the rack, and then they put
these switches on the inside of the rack.
What this ends up being is that
there's a set of switches in here.
These are the NV switches.
Then they run a bunch of cables.
Every single GPU has cables going
to the switches in the middle.
The switches have
connections to all the GPUs.
All of the GPUs can talk to all the
other GPUs in just two hops: going to
the switch, going to the other GPU.
Now, when I want to leave the rack,
I end up going via a different path.
The GPUs also have a much slower
connectivity, which is typically
about eight times slower.
The green that I drew here in
the GPU cases is the NVLink.
More generally, it's called
the scale-up network.
You will typically also have a
scale-out network, which allows you
to connect to some data center switch.
All
of the GPUs will have some connectivity
up to some data center switch somewhere.
This is
the scale-out, and
it tends to be about 8x slower
in bandwidth.
The challenge, if you want to lay out a
mixture of experts layer across two racks,
is that half of the GPUs here are going
to be wanting to talk to the GPUs here.
On average, when I look at where the
tokens on these GPUs want to go, half of
the tokens want to go inside the rack.
That's great.
They can use the fast scale-up network.
But half the tokens are going to
want to leave the rack and go to the
other rack, and that's not as good.
They need to use a much slower
network, and so that becomes the
bottleneck on the all-to-all pattern.
A different choice would be,
why don't I have a big switch
here and connect everything to
a much bigger switch that actually
combines the two racks together?
There are many ideas in this
direction, but in general, the
reason you have this hierarchy of
switches rather than one big switch
is to manage the cabling congestion.
You just need to run a
large number of cables.
Sorry, is that question you just asked
basically, why isn't it a bigger scale-up?
Exactly.
Why not just have a million chips
in scale-up or a thousand chips?
What has changed that has allowed Nvidia
to go from Hopper, which was 8, then
Blackwell is 72, and now Rubin will be...
is it 500 something?
Yeah, 500 and something.
What has allowed that to happen?
From Hopper to Blackwell is mostly
just the decision to switch from
trays as the form factor to switching
to racks as the form factor.
That's a product decision.
There wasn't a substantial
technical barrier there.
Switching from 64 to 500 or
so, there's a bit of Jensen math there,
but there is at least a genuine 4x
increase, which is coming from a much more
complicated and difficult rack design.
That is actually a new physical
design to run more cables.
The cable complication is just the cost
of figuring out which cable hops to which,
or which signal goes from what to what?
Let's zoom in on this and
look at the wire density.
I'll draw this diagram just once
more so we have a bit of a cleaner
and larger version to work with.
Let's say I have some
switches in the middle.
Initially, I'm going to start
with just two GPUs on each side
or two trays of GPUs on each side.
Let's say maybe each tray wants to
have two cables coming out of it.
I physically run vertical cables that look
like this running out to the switches.
Now if I want to double the
number of GPUs in a rack,
I need to run literally
twice the density of cables.
I need to run
these as well.
Extremely naive question.
But if you look at a physical
data center, it seems like there's
a lot of space within a rack.
I don't know.
The cables are really big and...
There is space outside the rack.
Inside the rack… As they become
more optimized, these racks are
very tight.
There's
connector density going from
the tray into the rack and the
rack's backplane, and the backplane
itself has a really high density.
There are other physical constraints
including the bend radius of cables.
You don't want to snap them and so on.
Okay, so it's literally the physical space
to put a cable that's constraining it.
I had no idea.
Interesting.
That seems surprising.
The
rack is so big and we can't
just stuff more cables in there.
Rack design is not my expertise,
but when I talk to folks on what
constraints they're up against,
it's a combination of things.
What are the big physical
things you're optimizing for?
Space, weight of the rack.
It's actually really heavy, so you
need enough metal to not sag and fall.
But then you add more
metal, and it's heavier.
Then power and cooling.
All of those are competing.
Modern racks are pushing all of those
to very extreme physical limits.
Deep work is by its nature quite
aversive, so even things which seem
like work, like Slack and email, can
be easy ways to distract yourself.
So I often wish that I could
just turn the internet off.
But if I'm prepping for an interview, even
if I have the papers and books on hand,
it's still super useful to be able to do a
back and forth with an LLM so I can break
down concepts and research follow-ups.
Google's new Gemma 4 is the first open
model that allows me to have this kind
of fully disconnected focus machine.
It's small enough to run on my laptop,
but good enough to actually be useful.
So to prep for this episode,
I downloaded Reiner's scaling
book and shut off the internet.
I was able to have Gemma help
me understand the material
and answer my questions.
If you want an LLM that you can run
locally on your laptop or even your
phone, you should check out Gemma 4.
When was GPT-4 released again?
Was it 2022 or 2023?
2023.
Okay.
And it was rumored to be
over one trillion parameters.
It seems like only now, within the last
six months, have models been getting
released that have significantly more
parameters than the model released three
years ago, when supposedly there should
have been this scaling in the meantime.
Is the reason that we were just
waiting for racks with enough memory
to hold a five-trillion parameter
model, along with its KV cache for
enough users for a lot of sequences?
Or if you're doing RL, a similar
consideration of actually
holding the KV cache for
the batch of problems
you're trying to solve.
If you look at Hopper, you
had eight Hoppers, and I think
that's 640 gigabytes as of 2022.
With Blackwell finally,
which was deployed in…?
Very recently.
Maybe last year.
Last year.
You finally have a scale-up on the
order of 10-20 terabytes, which is
enough for a 5T model plus KV cache.
Deploying in larger scale-up
domains is a huge unlock.
I've drawn here the Nvidia
Blackwell deployment.
The Google deployment has
actually had very large scale-up
domains for a long time.
That also explains why
Gemini seemed to be ahead.
It
just seems like Gemini has had
successful pre-training for longer
than some of the other labs.
Not having been there at the time,
I'm not sure how much is coming
from successfully deploying higher
sparsity ratios, which it could be.
It could also be a whole bunch
of actual modeling things,
specifically how you do
the mixture of experts.
We've seen
the DeepSeek mixture of experts activate
more experts, but finer-grained experts.
That was a big innovation.
I'm sure there are many other
innovations on the model architecture
as well as on the training data.
It's hard to disentangle all of
them, but what shows up in terms
of the limits of what you can do
is that the active parameters, as
we saw, are limited by the compute
cost, and the total parameters
are limited by the scale-up size.
When you're operating within a
single scale-up domain, is that
a consideration specifically for
either forward or backward, or
specifically for prefill versus decode?
Or is it preferred to always be
within a scale-up whatever kind
of workload you have, whether
you're doing a pre-training run, RL
generation, or inference for users?
Really interesting.
To answer that question, we're
going to need to talk about
the communication patterns.
We've talked about the mixture
of experts communication pattern.
That is this all-to-all.
All-to-all very strongly
favors full connectivity,
which is what we've just shown here,
and it favors being within one rack.
There are other kinds of parallelism
besides expert parallelism,
which we just showed here.
In the literature is
tensor parallelism.
With the trend towards smaller
experts, this has become much less
relevant, so we can ignore that.
But the other two things we have
available are data parallelism
and pipeline parallelism.
They can be a much better
fit for using multiple racks.
Let's focus on pipeline
parallelism specifically.
This is one layer of MoE.
I'm going to have a hundred
more layers up above.
I could decide at this point, for example,
to move to a different rack, change rack.
Now, is that going to become
a communication bottleneck?
We can actually solve for when this
becomes a communication bottleneck.
Before we do that algebraically, let's
visualize it out and sketch the path.
We're going to have another MoE layer,
and another MoE layer here, and so on.
Let's say I change rack here,
and then some number of layers
later, I change rack here as
well.
The methodology we're going to
use to determine whether we have
a communication bottleneck at the
point where we change rack is we're
going to compare the scale-out
bandwidth requirements to the
scale-up bandwidth requirements.
Let's write this.
The hint is going to be that
there's a lot more sends here.
We're sending many things here, whereas
we're only sending one thing here, and
we're also maybe doing it many times.
That's
what makes the difference.
Can I try to guess?
Just out of curiosity, to see if I'm
actually understanding, it seems like
you're sending batch size into the rack.
In here?
Yes.
But the communication within the rack
is batch size times number of GPUs.
Number of activated GPUs.
I don't send to this GPU at all.
There's an explosion from 1-3x
larger here in this diagram.
The key thing is that I didn't
even need to send to this GPU at
all, and so that's a big saving.
We're going to talk through
to what extent scale-up is
a bottleneck over scale-out.
We will directly jump to the ratio
of the time spent on scale-up
over the time spent on scale-out.
This is the quantity we're talking about.
The first consideration
is that scale-up is
8x faster than scale-out generally.
At a baseline, if the bandwidths
were the same, we would have this
1/8, which is coming from bandwidth.
But then we have some amount of
expansion in how much data we're sending.
If one token comes in here, then this
one token gets routed to, in the DeepSeek
case maybe 32 experts or 16 experts.
It gets routed to some number of experts.
So this is the number of
activated
experts.
This same thing applies on
multiple different layers, so
maybe I'm going to run two layers.
There's also multiple
times the number of layers
per stage.
Don't you need to multiply the whole
thing by two for the all-to-all?
For the up and down.
Yes, there's a factor of two.
Thank you.
What we would like is for the scale-up
time to be greater than the scale-out
time, because the scale-up time is the
more important and precious resource.
We would like this number to be
greater than or equal to one.
This really doesn't seem hard.
There's just a factor of 8
that we need to overcome.
So we need the product of these
three things to be bigger than 8.
Typically we have a fairly large
number of activated experts.
It could be 8 by itself.
Then we can increase the number of layers
per stage a lot until we satisfy this.
What this ends up looking like is that
I can have an entire pipeline of racks
where one rack does one layer, and
then I move on to the next rack and
do another layer, and then I move on
to the next rack and do another layer.
It's interesting to me that the best
parallelism strategy in practice
ends up being one which physically
resembles the actual architecture.
It's not some galaxy brain thing.
It's like, "Oh, we have experts, we're
going to put them on different GPUs,
or we have different layers, we're
just going to put them on different
racks." I feel that's interesting.
The cutting matches
the model architecture.
Exactly.
It could have been something wackier
with tensor parallelism and whatever.
The galaxy brain way to think of it is,
what are all the different dimensions
in which a model is scaled up?
It is scaled up by layers,
it is scaled up by the model dimension,
it is scaled up by the DFF dimension, it
is scaled up by the number of experts.
Every single one of those numbers
you can choose to cut along.
If those numbers are big
enough, it eventually becomes
profitable to cut along there.
We have selected two of them.
The other two, in the way models are
typically sized, are not profitable.
So there's a talk by Ilya where
he says, "Today we know not
to do pipeline parallelism."
And Horace He gave my friends
and me… I hate that it sounds
like a Dr. Seuss quote.
But he gave us a lecture on these
different kinds of parallelisms.
He said the problem with pipeline
parallelism is that, other than
the bubbles, it creates these
architectural constraints.
Kimi,
for example, has these residuals where
attention attends to layers a few back, so
it becomes hard to implement in this way.
I guess we didn't fully
articulate even what is the
benefit that we're getting from
pipelining.
These complexities are real.
Pipelining is a massive hassle,
but it does give you some benefits.
You can then decide whether those
benefits are worth the costs.
It has some benefits in inference,
maybe bigger benefits in training.
In inference, what are we saving on?
Are we saving on memory
time or compute time?
Not really.
We're just moving the memory time
from one chip to another chip,
or one rack to a different rack.
There's no actual benefit in runtime.
However, what we are saving
on is memory capacity.
If we think that the memory in a
rack is a bottleneck, then there's
a constraint on how fast we can go.
Pipelining allows us to
massively reduce that bottleneck.
The opposite connotation to this…
Before this interview, I was
chatting with Axel, who's a GPU
performance engineer at Jane Street.
He was explaining that to do
pipelining, you have to do
micro-batches rather than full batches.
If you do micro-batches, then
you're by definition not able to
amortize loading the weights across
all the users or all the sequences.
The positive connotation of that is
you don't have to use as much memory.
The negative connotation is that
we can't amortize loading the
weights across all those users.
Maybe it's worth explaining why
you have to do micro-batches.
Shall we draw the pipeline bubble?
What is this micro-batching
that shows up in pipeline
parallelism?
I'll focus on inference first.
It's a slightly simpler problem.
I'm going to draw time,
and then which rack
we're on.
The idea is that maybe
I'll have four racks.
I've got an inference that is
going to step through these four
racks in some time like this.
This is inference number zero.
It
runs at a certain batch size and steps
through all the pipeline stages like this.
Now, if we were to say, "Well, we're
going to run inference number one
here," this is clearly a massive waste.
Like three-quarters of the
time each of the racks is doing
nothing.
We don't actually run inference one here,
we run it as soon as we can, which is
immediately after inference zero finishes.
And
then we keep going.
If we hadn't filled this in, we
would call this the pipeline bubble.
When I've drawn it in this inference
context where we're only going
in a forwards pass, it's obvious.
Why would you do this stupid thing?
In a training context,
it's maybe less obvious.
But in the inference context, it's
really natural to make this change.
Oh, interesting.
This is sort of obvious, but the
difference between micro-batch and batch
doesn't matter at all in inference because
you can just call it whatever you want.
It only matters in training because
there is an optimal batch size.
Yes.
Before you do a full backward
step, you want to have accumulated
all the sequences in that batch.
If you want to do
pipelining in training, in order
to avoid that bubble, you need to—
Should we draw the training diagram
with that?
Let’s do that.
This is the inference diagram, and
I'll call this forward so we don't
have the wrong thing showing up there.
Let's do the same thing for training now.
We've got a forwards pass, but at
some stage we're going to have to
transition to a backwards pass.
We'll do some number of
batches in the forwards pass,
and then we're going to transition to
the backwards pass for everyone all
in one go.
The inference part is the same here,
but then we do a hard stop at this point
and transition everyone to the backwards
pass, with similar numbering like this.
It may be worth clarifying the
reason there is that hard stop
is because you want to do a whole
batch at once for the backward step.
And then there is an optimal size
for how big that batch should be.
Smaller is always better,
actually, is a way to put it.
From an ML convergence rate
perspective, smaller is always better
because you're getting the freshest
information from the gradient descent.
But from a total training
time perspective?
From a total training time
perspective, smaller is worse
from a systems perspective.
The optimum is the
trade-off between those two.
So you pick a batch size, and
for that batch size, you do some amount
forwards and then some amount backwards.
You asked why there is
even a hard stop there.
With pipeline parallelism, because
you've got this idle time here which
is the bubble, there are so many
techniques in the literature for how to
lay this out differently and avoid that.
There are more complicated schemes called
zero bubble or one-forward-one-backward,
which interweave the forwards and
the backwards in complicated ways.
You can mine Bitcoin in that bubble.
Right.
More usefully, you can do
the weight gradient step, but
you can also mine Bitcoin.
In inference, the effect of pipelining
on anything you care about, like
batch size or latency, is neutral.
It doesn't improve it,
it doesn't make it worse.
If you look at the latency of this
inference, running it if it were pipelined
versus if it were all on one rack… If it
were all on one rack, we would just slide
all the boxes down and still put them in
a row, and the latency would be the same.
Pipelining
is neither better nor worse for latency.
It does mean that you just use
less memory capacity per rack.
Because now instead of needing the
whole model, you only need a quarter
of the model, and you can expand.
Makes a ton of sense.
So it's a no-brainer to use pipelining
during inference, but there's this
harder trade-off during training.
Even in inference, in
fact, it is not used a ton.
It reduces your memory capacity
requirements, but there's
actually a huge surplus.
I think you were saying that a rack of
Blackwell has many tens of terabytes.
That's much bigger than a
trillion parameter model.
A trillion parameter model only needs
one terabyte, so it already fits.
There's not a huge benefit from
pipelining because you're reducing a
number that's already pretty small.
But it does say that theoretically,
maybe you had too much memory there.
You could have
built different hardware
that has less memory.
If you were designing your hardware,
you could say, "I didn't need that
much memory because I don't need
the weights to fit in one rack.
I can fit the weights in eight racks,
then I could have built hardware that
didn't have so much HBM per GPU."
Last week, Horace He was kind enough to
give me and my friends a great lecture
on large-scale pre-training systems.
And there were some concepts that
I wanted to animate for a write-up
on my blog, like how weights shard
and gradients flow depending on
the parallelism that you're using.
So I gave Cursor my lecture notes and a
sketch that I made during the lecture.
And I asked it to visualize a
specific hierarchical collective
that Horace had explained.
The first version was already pretty
good, and then I was able to use
design mode to select and tweak
any specific components from there.
I was able to do all of this
without a clear end state in mind.
Cursor's Composer 2 Fast model was
quick enough that I was able to
iterate almost instantaneously.
I could try an idea, test the
results in the built-in browser,
and immediately make any changes.
I went through 10 different
versions in under 20 minutes.
If you want to check out this
animation, I published it along with
the lecture notes in a blog post.
The link is in the description.
And if you want to try out this kind of
iterative design flow for yourself, go
to cursor.com/dwarkesh to get started.
everybody's talking about
the memory wall right now.
Memory is getting super expensive.
There's not enough memory.
Smartphone volume will go down 30%
because there's not enough memory.
This is shocking, Dylan said
hyperscalers are spending 50% of
their CapEx this year on memory.
That’s believable.
What is hyperscaler CapEx?
That's high hundreds of billions,
maybe a trillion, and they're
spending half of that on memory?
That is a huge constraint.
That's why we're not going to get
new laptops and phones this year.
But at the same time,
we have too much memory?
People are willing to put too
much memory into these systems.
Why is Jensen shoving all this memory
into these racks if you don't need it?
In the equations we had here before we
erased them, we were doing memory time,
memory bandwidth and compute bandwidth.
Let's now start looking
at memory capacity.
We'll start off with memory
capacity without even thinking
about a parallelism scheme.
The demand on memory is the
number of total parameters.
This is what we need to fit the weights
in some system that we are using.
Then we need to fit the KVs as well.
KVs go as batch size times
the length of the context
times the bytes per
token.
What I was arguing about in this
context, and the case I was making
for pipelining, is that there are some
techniques that allow us to solve this.
Let's consider running this
on some number of GPUs.
We're going to have one extent, which
is E, the expert
parallelism.
When we had this sharding of an
expert layer across many GPUs,
to what extent do we do that?
How many GPUs?
We're going to say that
this is, for example 64.
Then P is going to be the extent of
pipelining.
This is the number of racks,
maybe we'll pick 4 or something
like that.
This is the total memory
requirement across the system,
but now I'm going to calculate a
memory requirement per GPU.
I'll use a lowercase
cmem.
Obviously, we just take all
of these numbers and divide
it by E and P. Really easy.
It's
this Ntotal, plus the batch times
length of context times bytes per
token, all divided by E times P.
Why is this correct as divided this way?
We knew that the parameters were perfectly
divided amongst all the GPUs in a rack.
The layers are perfectly divided
amongst the different racks.
So that works here.
Somehow we're going to arrange—I'll
hand-wave exactly how—the same
perfect sharding of the contexts
across GPUs in a rack, and then
based on layer across racks.
Sorry, 4 is the number of racks?
Yeah, for
example.
This is the place where we actually need
to go back and analyze this batch size B.
You were making this comment that
there's micro-batching versus global
batching.
Let's come back to this
pipelining diagram here.
We've got one batch going forward
here, and then as I drew it,
it kind of just disappeared.
That's not really correct.
If you think about how decode is
working, I have a bunch of tokens
that I have generated already.
I do one forwards pass where
I generate a new token,
and then I write that to my KV cache.
Then I do another forwards pass
that generates the next token.
I'm actually going to be running
this batch zero in a loop.
In fact, I go forwards.
Once I finish, I can start the
next iteration of the loop up here.
We'll just
fill this in.
We've got the two,
three, two and three, and two and three.
Let's split this batch.
This batch will be the global batch size.
B is going to be the number
of micro-batches times
the batch size per micro-batch.
How many micro-batches do we need?
The number of micro-batches in this
diagram is 4: zero, one, two, three.
The micro-batch size is
still this 2000-ish number.
Sorry, no, this is the
300 times sparsity.
This is
how big the train that takes
off every 20 milliseconds is.
Right.
This is going to be the
20-millisecond train.
The global batch size is the number of
micro-batches times the local batch size.
Local batch size is set by
this hardware parameter.
The number of micro-batches
is as small as possible, such that we can
wrap around and not leave any idle time.
If we had fewer, we would have
this idle time when we wrap around.
You can visually see that it is equal
to the number of pipeline stages.
It's a proof by visual here.
It is 4, and it's 4 this way as well.
You can look and see that it goes
along here, and then it wraps around
to the number of pipeline stages.
Sorry, very basic question.
Is this what is actually done?
A frontier model today will have
pipelining during inference?
For sure during massive
scale training this is done.
It can be done for inference.
I'm actually going to make the
case for why it is less attractive.
It is useful for weights,
but not so useful for KVs.
The
big challenge is... Let's fill this in.
The micro-batch size here ends up being
equal to the number of pipeline stages.
When we go back and substitute
all of that into here,
we get
a number of pipeline stages times
this little b showing up in here.
When we factor this out, I'm going
to split this plus into two terms.
We
get the full division
by E times P over here.
We still have division by E times
P over here, but the Ps cancel.
What we find is that if you increase
the number of pipeline stages, the
memory footprint for the number of
weights keeps going down and down and
down, but the memory footprint for the
number of activations stays constant.
So it doesn't actually work.
Most of your memory…
Once you do enough pipelining—and it's
really not much, even two is often
enough—this term becomes very small.
The KV cache becomes the dominant term.
I know this is wrong.
I'm just trying to think about why
my train of logic here is wrong.
If
you're pipelining through many
different stages, the KV values
are not shared between layers.
Why would it not help to be
pipelining across multiple layers?
Because then you don't have to store...
You only need to store one layer
rather than two layers of KVs.
It helps from that
perspective, you're right.
What's competing with that, though,
is that you need to be keeping all
of the racks usefully busy at a time,
so the number of sequences that are
in flight simultaneously has gone up.
Ah, that makes sense.
Those exactly cancel, and you end
up not getting a saving per GPU.
Right.
This is going back fundamentally
to the point of how you're not
able to amortize across KV caches.
First, we established you can’t
amortize KV caches across batch size.
Now we're saying you also can't
shard it across pipeline stages.
It sucks from both of
those points of view.
Interesting.
So then what is done during inference?
The DeepSeek paper reports what
they do, which is that they just
do a lot of expert parallelism.
In effect, you should increase your expert
parallelism up to your scale-up domain
size, and then do very little pipelining.
Maybe none at all, maybe two,
just enough to make the weight
storage not too big of an issue.
Those are the only two parallelisms
that really make sense.
In the past, there was tensor parallelism,
which was cutting up within an expert,
but the experts are so small now that
that is not a profitable optimization.
Does that mean that frontier labs,
when they're doing inference, are
just within a single scale-up?
Yes.
You can look at how it
depends on model size.
You could have a very large model,
one that exceeds the memory of a rack.
There you should be doing
a bit of pipelining.
Maybe it's extremely sparse, for example,
and that would be a reason to do it.
This goes back to the promise
at the beginning of the lecture,
which was this will actually tell
you about AI progress as well.
To the extent it is the case that model
size scaling has been slow until recently…
Let me make sure I understand the claim.
The claim would not be you could
have trained across more racks.
It was just that it would not have made
sense before, we didn't have the ability
to do inference for a bigger model easily.
Actually, pipelining doesn't
help with context length.
It totally helps with model size.
Because of the ability to do
pipelining, a rack at least should
not be a constraint on your ability
to fit the model parameters.
The other consideration you're asking
is, why hasn't it scaled up more, and
why did bigger scale-up domains help?
We talked through one aspect
of that, which is that it's
not because of memory capacity.
We have a solution to the memory capacity
at least with respect to model size,
not with respect to KV cache size but
at least with respect to model size.
The other issue that shows up is latency.
I was just about to ask, going from rack
to rack, what is the latency cost per hop?
This is very much
dependent on the hardware.
I can't say with a lot of authority.
I think it's probably on the order of
a few milliseconds, but it could be
off by an order of magnitude there.
Is 4 a realistic number of how many
pipelining stages you might have?
Yes.
So that's not that much.
On a small number of pipelining stages,
this is not a huge latency impact.
But I guess it's 10
milliseconds per token.
That's right.
2 times 4-ish, or I don't know
how many you said… 10 milliseconds
per token is actually a lot.
If it goes from 20 to 30, or something
like that…
Just to chart the path that it goes
through, here you're going from your
GPU or TPU to a network card, which
then goes to a top-of-rack switch,
and then hops over to the other rack
and does the same thing in reverse.
You have to sum up the latencies
of these different things.
Sorry, is this the same thing
as the data center switch?
It may in fact go up to a
data center switch and back.
It depends on deployment configuration.
Got it.
And because it's decode and sequential,
they stack up across the stages.
You can't do them at the same time.
That’s right.
This brings us back to the question
then, is the size of the scale-up at
all relevant to why AI model sizes
have been what they have been over
the last few years, whether through
training or through inference?
We talked about latency of the hop.
There is also just the tmem
latency.
The memory time latency is
actually massively improved
by larger scale-up domains.
I'll recall tmem down here.
tmem for the weights
was equal to the number
of total parameters
divided by the memory bandwidth.
Which memory bandwidth
are we talking about here?
Is it just one GPU?
It
is the number of GPUs that I can use
in parallel to load these weights.
I can't use different pipeline stages
in parallel because they're not
running at the same time, but I can
use all the GPUs in my scale-up domain
in parallel to load the weights.
This is actually extremely effective.
Basically, I end up with a term
here, this memory bandwidth term
itself is equal to scale-up size...
Times memory bandwidth per GPU.
Yeah.
Times GPU
bandwidth.
This term doesn't increase a lot.
It maybe increases 1.5 or 2x per
generation, but this one increased
by a factor of 8 from Hopper.
So the reason the bigger scale-up matters,
it's not the memory capacity of the whole
scale-up, but really the memory bandwidth.
Yeah.
Pipelining totally solves
the capacity problem, but
scale-up size helps solve
the bandwidth problem.
And the bandwidth problem helps
you do longer context lengths,
which is more and more relevant
as these models get more agentic.
It lets you just run the model at
lower latency as a first thing.
If I just do a very sparse model
and it's on a little H100 box,
the latency will be really high.
A super tangential question.
There's Chinchilla scaling, which
tells you how big a model should
be relative to the amount of
data you're going to train it on.
But now, obviously, you're not just trying
to optimize for the highest quality model
you could get with training compute.
You want the best results a
user can get with a mixture of
training and inference compute.
So there's a question of how much
you should over-train a model
such that compute amortized over
training and inference is minimized
to get a certain performance.
But now with RL, there's another
consideration which is, you're going
to do some amount of pre-training.
That pre-training will be used
both for RL generation and then
for inference for the final user.
By over-training here I mean that while it
would have been more efficient just from
a training compute perspective to have a
bigger model that you train for less time
because it can learn faster, maybe you
get a smaller model, spend more compute
training it than you otherwise would have,
but now it's cheaper to give it to users.
Let me make the question more concrete.
Basically, how much more than Chinchilla
optimal are models over-trained?
And has that changed as a
result of RL generation?
This is a place where we have to do a
bit of guesswork because the updated
scaling laws and the model traffic are
not reported, so we have to guess there.
One way to look at it…
Let me first just make a
general heuristic claim.
If I have some cost, and I've got a
total cost which is a sum of cost A
and cost B, like maybe this is the
training cost and this is the inference
cost, and I want to minimize this sum…
For many
curves, the minimum tends to be
where the costs are equalized.
That's something of a heuristic claim, but
there are many examples where it's true.
Where one is 1/x and the other one is x,
for example, they tend to be minimized
at the point where they equal each other.
It's also true for ex and e-x
and all kinds of other things.
Basically, I've got some curve
that's going down, some other curve
that's going up, and they tend to
be minimized at this equal point.
Heuristically,
I will conjecture that that is
true for the setup you described as
well.
Actually showing that would be
true would require looking at the
scaling laws and fitting these weird
exponents, but things that follow
power laws tend to have this property.
So I'll just make that claim and move on.
We're going to say that we want
to equalize the cost of training
and the cost of inference.
We can do all of it in general.
The cost of pre-training,
that's the number of
active params times the
data on pre-training.
There's a factor of 6 out here,
which is the number of FLOPs.
There's the famous 6ND formula.
Then
in RL, we have approximately
the same thing.
We've got the same number of
active parameters, but now the
amount of data is the RL data.
There is this extra efficiency
multiplier, or inefficiency...
Which is the fact that you're not
training on all your rollouts.
Well, there's that, and then
the other, perhaps even bigger
inefficiency is that this involves
a substantial amount of decode.
Often decode runs at
less MFU than training.
Okay.
So if you're doing a backward
pass on every single generation
in RL, it would be 6ND.
So this could be a smaller number, right?
It
would at least be two,
because that's the lower...
Somewhere in the range of two to six.
We'll say somewhere in the
range of two to six and leave it
at that.
Then we can add in the inference cost.
The inference cost is two, the
number of active parameters
times the data in inference.
Sorry, I think the way I
said it was super garbled.
Just for the audience,
forward plus backwards per parameter is 6.
Forward alone is 2.
That's why RL, where you're definitely
going to generate all the trajectories
but you might or might not train
all the trajectories, is 2 to 6.
Yes.
Thank you.
And then inference is just 2.
We're going to solve for essentially
equality of all three of these terms.
That is the ballpark of
where people are going to be.
Labs have more information on what
is productive in doing more RL, for
example, versus doing more pre-training.
I don't have that information,
but I think a good ballpark is a
33% split between each of them.
I'm not sure I understand
the intuition for that.
Another naive model could have been
that RL plus pre-training would
be 50% and inference would be 50%.
That's also a valid answer.
Because this is heuristic, I can't
really argue for one versus the other.
They don't differ by that much.
Thirty-three versus twenty-five
is only a small factor off.
Let's pick one of them.
All equal seems simple enough,
so we're just going to
solve for equality of them.
It's pretty straightforward.
We can immediately see that the
number of activated parameters totally
disappears, so let's factor that out.
We're going to just say that data in
pre-training—I decided to do it your
way, it's a little bit nicer—plus...
Oh,
I didn't have the
inefficiency over here either.
Data
in pre-training plus some multiple
of α times the data in RL is
going to end up equal to some
β times the data in inference.
Let's just roughly size the α.
This α
is maybe somewhere in the range of 2 to 6.
Over 6, from this term
compared to this term.
And then we've got an inefficiency
term, which I would say is
maybe in the range of 30%.
So this alpha is going
to be something like
1/10.
And this β here is actually the same.
It's a third.
It's one third times 30%.
So it also equals 1/10.
If both of them are one in ten,
that kind of implies that there's
never a backward pass on RL?
Yeah.
Okay, we can make this 2/10.
Make it a bit bigger.
Just write it out once more,
this is 2/10, this is 1/10.
The number of inference tokens you
have is just a function of hundreds
of millions of tokens per second times
my model is deployed for two months
before I ship to the next version.
That should determine
the number of tokens
in RL and pre-training.
I guess we didn't do the
equivalence between pre-training
and RL, so we'll do that here.
Data in pre-training should be
equal to 2/10 data in RL for
them to be cost equivalent.
Sorry, 1/10.
I got it backwards.
We pay more cost when it's
inefficient, so this needs to be 1/10.
Tracing this back… This thing ends
up actually being, as written here…
This is like 1.5, and this is one.
Billions of dollars worth of compute
just flowed in the other direction.
Right?
I think if you do it with a
spreadsheet and actually model
it out, you might notice when
the money’s going down the drain.
All of these end up being
close in, as modeled here.
This 30% may have been a
little bit too generous.
So let's say something like 1.5
here, and leave this as a one here.
I think at this point, you
can almost read it off.
The number of inference tokens should
be about the same as the number of
pre-training tokens, which should
be about the same as the number
of RL tokens, within factors that
we're not able to reason about.
Sorry for making a basic algebra mistake.
It seems like there should be fewer
RL tokens than pre-training tokens?
That's in general right.
Because RL is less efficient
in terms of machine time,
if you're trying to equalize the
RL and pre-training time, then
you should have fewer tokens in
order to have the same wall time.
This is all quite interesting.
I never thought about it in
terms of equalizing data.
I think starting with equalizing
in cost is right, but depending
on how you model the cost, this
comes close to equalizing in data.
So for GPT to be trained optimally,
every single user who uses GPT-5,
the total amount of tokens that they
stream should equal the total amount
that has gone into pre-training.
And the total amount of tokens
that have gone into pre-training
is the sum of all human knowledge.
Each model should generate the
sum of human knowledge on the
output that it gets on the input.
Yeah.
Which way are people going to err?
If you think that people's power of
prediction is not perfect, and also you
run the risk that you make a model that
is not a frontier model and then you
just throw it away, then that changes
the cost trade-off because there's some
probability that applies to the inference.
And you should derate the
inference tokens by some amount.
Right.
Can we back out how much more
compute than Chinchilla optimal
for a given sized model?
I think we just have to make some
real-world assumptions here in order to do
that.
The inference tokens, we should
totally be able to count, right?
Let's say a few hundred million.
Maybe it's five hundred million tokens
a second now, I don't really know.
Five hundred million
tokens a second times.
A model is deployed for two
months before it becomes obsolete?
I
can't do this in my head.
Can you type it into a computer?
2.6 x 1015.
Okay.
This number is probably too
large because this is going to
be multiple models in a family.
Let's make it
5x smaller or 10x smaller or something
like that.
So we're estimating maybe fifty million
tokens per second, per specific model.
The model is live for two months.
This comes out to around
two hundred trillion tokens.
And then we want to compare that to
active parameters on a frontier model.
I don't actually know the latest rumors.
Do
you know?
Somebody told me a hundred
and fifty trillion.
Active parameters?
Sorry, I meant tokens.
Trained on a hundred and
fifty trillion tokens.
Interesting.
Which is similar.
That's actually similar.
So data on pre-training.
This is not well-cited but it’s fine.
I think often the number
of active parameters
could be in the range of
a hundred billion, something like that.
Maybe a bit larger.
So multiply by 20 to get
the Chinchilla token count.
So Chinchilla, DChinchilla,
would be around two trillion.
We see we're about a hundred
times larger than that.
What does DChinchilla actually mean?
The token count for pre-training
that the Chinchilla scaling
law would recommend, I guess.
Oh, I see.
So how much is it over-trained?
Got it.
The ratio of this two hundred trillion
or a hundred trillion parameters over the
Chinchilla optimal of two trillion,
that's the amount it's over-trained.
Which is a factor of a
hundred over-trained.
A hundred.
So if you consider this right here,
to the extent this is in the right
ballpark, just by thinking about how you
want everything to be equal in terms of
compute… If OpenAI also realizes that
and they're serving a certain amount of
tokens per second, that tells you how much
data went into the pre-training of GPT-5.
Even if it's 50% off or something, it
is wild that you can first-principles
these kinds of numbers.
This is why you should just
approximate everywhere, because
there are big error bars on this.
But it's kind of empowering to just
set A equal to B and figure it out.
That's super cool.
Okay, so in the spirit of trying to
deduce things, we can publicly look
up the API prices of these models, and
maybe we can learn something from that.
First, with longer context, Gemini 3.1
is 50% more expensive if you go over 200k
tokens than if you're below 200k tokens.
At a high level, I understand why
that might be, but why specifically
50%?
Why specifically 50%?
The high level, even in the first
place, is that there is some amount of
increasing cost with context length.
We can bring that back up.
That was
the memory time versus the compute time.
We've put up these same equations
from before, of the time for memory
fetches which is the weights and
the KV cache, and then the time for
the compute which is just the matrix
multiplications for the weights.
I will also draw the cost curve, but
this time I'll do it as a function of
context length instead of batch size.
So this is the cost curve as
a function of context length.
We'll draw the compute.
The cost of the compute is actually
constant as a function of context length.
There's no dependence
here on context length.
In reality, there is some dependence,
but it is very mild, so we'll ignore it.
So this is the time for the compute.
Then we'll also draw the dependence
of the memory fetch on context length.
This starts at a large number
for the weights and then grows
gradually with the context length.
Maybe starting here, and then grow
gradually with context length.
And
so, you take the maximum and you see
there is this inflection point here.
So this is the cost that
Gemini might be paying.
And then you think, how might you put
a pricing structure on top of that?
You would like to ensure that no
matter what the context length
is, you are still profitable.
So we've got a two-tier pricing structure.
Maybe we've got something that
looks like this up to some extent.
I think it says something about,
given that the bump is at 200k, it
probably means that this is somewhat
aligned with this crossover point.
Maybe not exactly aligned with it.
We can actually probably even
complete that calculation just
to see where it lands out.
We can solve for the number of bytes
per token if we make some assumptions
about the number of active parameters.
So solving for the number of bytes
per token, we're going to assume
the point where we equalize the time
of memory and the time of compute
is at, let's say, 200k tokens.
So we equalize these two.
We're also going to assume that the batch
size is large enough that the memory
time spent on weights is negligible.
So we'll forget about this,
and we'll focus on the actual
memory time spent on KV cache.
That ends up saying, copying this term
over, batch times length of context times
bytes per token over memory bandwidth
is going to be equal to
the number of activated
params over FLOPs.
And then we're going to
solve for bytes per token.
Batch size was missing here.
It shows up here, and then it cancels
out by the time we get to here.
And I dropped the length of context.
So we can plug in numbers.
This is the reciprocal of the
number that we saw before.
This is 1/300, which is reasonably stable
across many different hardware platforms.
We conjecturally said that
maybe the number of activated
parameters is a hundred billion.
The length of the
context we said was 200k.
Something is wrong here, though.
Length of the context should
be on the denominator, not the numerator.
1667. Almost two kilobytes.
That is plausible, actually.
You said around two kilobytes.
Let's just do a sanity check
for what this could be.
There are two mechanisms that
people do attention with a
small number of bytes per token.
One is dense attention with
a lot of reuse across layers.
Character AI has a blog post talking about
that, alternating long and short context.
In the Character AI kind of model,
which also showed up in the Gemma
models, the global context—which
is really what we're talking about
here—was shared across all the layers.
To get this to kilobytes, you
could get that, for example, as
a dhead of 128, which is typical.
Then
the number of bytes is typically
the number of attention layers
times two times dhead times
the number of KV heads.
This is the number of
unique contexts per layer.
Do you share the context across many
layers, or do you use it only once?
In the Character AI-like
models, this number is one.
We said this is 128.
This is a choice which
typically ranges from one...
Sorry, this is KV heads, I meant.
The difference between a
head and a KV head is that…?
The KV heads are the heads that
are stored in memory, store the
contents of the previous tokens.
The Q heads are the retrieval heads.
They're only used temporarily and
they’re used by the attending token.
In this autoregressive context, I've
got KV heads associated with all
of the contexts, and then Q heads
associated with this new token here.
But this head, the
128.
Oh, sorry.
This d-head is the
dimension of the vector.
The
number of KV heads is typically
in the range of 1 to 8.
It is totally plausible to get
this by, for example, having 8
KV heads and a d-head of 128.
That gives you exactly this number.
Or you could have fewer
KV heads, but more layers.
This is one way to get
there via dense attention.
There's also a way to get there
via sparse attention, where you
increase all of these numbers, but
then you have a 1/sparsity term.
I think this number is plausible,
if maybe a little bit small.
It's funny that they would leak so much
information through their API pricing.
I mean, you are incentivized to
price close to your costs because
otherwise someone could scoop you.
Maybe we can learn something about
the difference in input versus output
prices, and what that tells us about
decode versus prefill in these models.
I think last I checked it's 50% more
expensive or something like that?
I don't remember.
What I've seen in the past
is 3-5x more expensive.
Okay, that makes more sense.
So let's say it's 5x more expensive.
This is the compute to process
the next token in decode.
Suppose you're doing prefill, where
you're not just processing the most
recent token, you're processing
all the tokens in parallel.
I want to say that it would
be this times length prefill?
Or length of the pass in general.
If we can think of decode as
being a pass with one, and then
prefill being a pass with many.
Okay.
So maybe prefix?
Okay,
memory.
You're not storing the KV cache for
the tokens that are the prefill tokens.
Let's actually draw how prefill
shows up here, if I may clarify.
We do a bit of decode like this.
We may actually come
back and do more prefill.
If you think this is a chat session, the
user says something, the AI generates
a response, and then the user says
something else and we prefill this.
Maybe this is the general
case, rather than this.
In fact, this is like you
read a file or something.
Read a file or the AI is responding
to a user input, tool call, or
anything that's not AI-generated.
Okay, suppose we're here.
You will have calculated
all of this previously.
So just the KV of
everything that came before.
But what is the memory cost of this?
Well, the
memory bandwidth cost of this.
If you're doing flash attention, it would—
It's basically temporary.
It doesn't even go to main memory.
Just ignore that.
Exactly.
So then it would just be
everything that came before.
Is it not just that then?
There's actually no adjustment
at all to the memory time.
Okay.
Great.
So it's a very trivial
change to accommodate.
This
term is making it 5x more expensive.
Now, why would that be?
What
does that actually tell us?
What variable does this help us clamp?
The
only thing that could have
changed is that the compute is
5x more expensive as a result.
This is the time for one pass,
but actually the amount of
tokens is that much larger.
We want the cost per token, in
fact, or the time per token.
I'm not sure I understood.
This
is for processing the
next token in prefix?
Well, actually for
processing the entire batch.
At this cost, we have processed this
many tokens, the length of prefill.
Or I guess the length of the pass.
Not this prefix, but it's this cost.
Okay.
Let's just do this pass.
So this is 5x more expensive.
Input is 5x more expensive.
Output is more expensive, in fact.
Output is 5x more expensive.
The result we want to work towards is
that prefill is compute-limited and
decode is memory bandwidth-limited.
Why don't we do this?
Why don't we just chart it with len-pass
on the X-axis and t on the Y-axis.
We want the cost per
token, so it'll be t over
length of the pass.
That'll be
right.
I
guess I’m getting confused by this.
Len-pass is... It seems like this should
be higher when you're doing prefill.
Prefill has a bigger length pass.
Yeah.
But then why is it cheaper?
Why is the cost higher?
It's this division by length pass.
This is going to divide out, but
then all of this is going to divide
by length of pass, and it's going
to make the memory costs cheaper.
Okay.
Let me think about this then.
Basically we'll have four different lines.
Let's do
prefill first...
Actually, let's do decode first.
Length of the pass, when
it's one, that is decode.
When it is bigger, that is prefill.
Oh, okay.
I see.
That makes sense.
Getting back to it.
So tcompute, if you have
basically just this divided by
len-pass, so just this amount.
This actually does not vary based on t, so
it'll just be some flat value like this.
And this is tcompute.
And
this is—
That's decode.
Decode.
Right.
Now tmem, we have this whole
thing divided by len-pass.
Well, it doesn't really matter
what's up there, it'll just be
something that looks like this.
Let's say this is tmem.
This is decode again.
So as the length of the prefix goes
up, or pass, your memory bandwidth time
declines, and that means that to the
extent that you were bottlenecked on
memory bandwidth before, you can avoid
being bottlenecked on memory bandwidth.
The fact that they are charging 5x less
for prefill than decode does suggest that
they are bottlenecked on memory bandwidth
to quite a degree, such that for them at
least—because t is equivalent to cost,
it's the cost of renting a compute—this
would be at 1, and this would be at 5.
That's right.
So it is, in fact, tremendously
memory bandwidth bottlenecked.
The real graph looks something like
that.
It still crosses, but yeah.
Exactly.
Let me do it this way.
This is
the gap on decode between the
memory and the compute time.
Okay, interesting.
Another interesting one would be
why cache hits are so much cheaper.
If I remember correctly, cache hits
are like 10x… It's more expensive
to write to cache according to
the pricing on all these models.
But if you do hit a cache, it's
10x.
Presumably, this is the cost
of keeping something in HBM
rather than just evacuating it.
But if you do keep it in HBM,
then it's cheaper to load again?
Right.
There are two ways you can produce the KV
cache for a token.
You can just produce it from
scratch by computing it from the
underlying token IDs, which are tiny.
Or
you can previously have produced
it and stored it in a memory
somewhere.
The cost ratio is really talking
about the ratio between those
two mechanisms of producing it.
A cache miss means you've deleted it
from all your memories, and you have to
recompute it from the tokens directly.
You can even take that a step
further and think about which
memory tier you store it in.
You could store it in HBM.
There are other slower and cheaper
memories than HBM, like DDR
on your host or flash as well.
One of the things you can do is a
calculation of where it makes sense to be
in each memory tier, and this is related
to how long you're going to store it for.
We want to look at the cost of storage
in a few different memory tiers and
also the cost of rematerialization.
Remat means the cost to rebuild all
of the KV cache from scratch after you
deleted it, so we rematerialize it.
Basically, this is going to
cost the length of the context.
Actually, we'll look at the cost per
token, so we don't need to carry around
this length of context everywhere.
To rematerialize one token of
KV cache, I just need to run a
forward pass on the whole model.
This is going to be the compute time.
I have to rerun the compute at whatever
speed my GPU does it, and then I
multiply it by my GPU dollars per second.
Sorry, excuse a naive question.
Why is there not a quadratic term?
There is a quadratic term.
It shows up in the compute.
As an approximation, I chose to remove it.
I'll just show you quickly
what that looks like.
If you look at the
cost per token, or the number of
FLOPs per token, there are the FLOPs
that are coming from doing the weight
matrix multiplies as a function of—
Which is flat.
...context length.
And then there is the number of
multiplies that comes from doing the
KV cache, which goes up linearly with
the amount of stuff you attend to.
The slope on this is so low that
when you draw it like this, it's very
well approximated by a flat line.
You start to notice the effect of
the quadratic or the linear term
up in the millions of tokens or so.
So it's just not super relevant.
So what is the reason that there's
no company which has over a million
token context length, if this is true?
There are two costs of long context.
One is the memory bandwidth cost, which
we've spent a lot of time analyzing.
That's this thing.
The other one is the compute cost.
The compute cost is
almost always forced by
fundamental principles to
be a much smaller slope than
the memory bandwidth cost.
The primary things that limit you
to really large contexts are memory
bandwidth and memory capacity,
which is exactly this effect.
There's this idea that Dario said on
the podcast, and others have said, which
is, "We don't need continual learning
for AGI, in-context learning is enough."
If you believe that, then you have
to think that we have to get to a
hundred-million-token context length to
have an employee that is the equivalent
of working with you for a month.
Now, maybe that's no longer true
with sparse attention or something.
But if you think that, then some ML
infra thing would have to change to
allow for a hundred million, like
the memory bandwidth, to allow for a
hundred-million-token context lengths.
Sparse attention gives you a get-out for
sure, because you get this square root.
It gives you a big improvement.
But if you look at the history
of context lengths of models,
from earlier models like GPT-3, maybe
to GPT-4—I don't remember when the
transition happened exactly—they
shot up from about 8K to 100-200K.
And then for the last year or two,
they've all been hovering around there.
I think that indicates that this
is the reasonably balanced cost
point, and going massively beyond
that would be cost-prohibitive.
Not because of the compute cost,
because of the memory bandwidth...
Because of memory bandwidth cost, yeah.
I actually don't see a very
good path to solving that.
The HBM is where it is.
It's not getting hugely better.
And why doesn't sparse attention solve it?
Sparse attention is a big improvement.
Maybe that is priced in already, perhaps.
It's not an infinite improvement
because if you go too sparse,
you lose too much quality.
The empirical result is that the context
lengths haven't been increasing that much.
I think it's because there is no
solution to the memory wall here.
Going too sparse just means you're
attending to a very small subset of the
tokens, and the quality will get worse.
Makes sense.
What is the cost of
these different ways of
resynthesizing the KV cache?
Computing it from scratch
is based on my GPU time.
I have to do a certain amount
of multiplies, of GPU time
that I spend in order to
produce it.
Storing in
HBM.
This really goes as my
bytes per token.
I need to just have some number
of bytes per token, and then I
need to store this in the HBM.
It's going to use up
some of my HBM capacity.
A way to think of this is that if
I have too many of these things
sitting in my HBM, if I fill up my
HBM with just KV caches that I'm
not using, I can't use that GPU.
How do I price that?
Maybe I say that the cost
of it is proportional to the
fraction of the HBM I'm using.
There's also times GPU dollars.
Let's just do one more memory tier and say
store in DDR instead.
The same kind of thing goes
up for flash and for DDR.
I put these in the wrong columns.
I meant to make two columns.
The distinction I want to make
is that there is the cost to
retrieve, and then there's a cost to
hold on.
This is a cost per second, whereas
this is an instantaneous cost.
Rematerialization has a cost to
retrieve and has zero cost to
store it because we've deleted it.
This is the one that I
put in the wrong location.
This is actually the cost just
to hold on, so I will rewrite it.
If we're just storing it in HBM,
it has this sort of cost profile.
If
we store in DDR, it's actually
going to take some time.
We get the same thing here:
bytes per token over DDR capacity
times DDR cost per
second.
But now this has a cost to retrieve
that is higher than the HBM because
we need to copy it into the HBM.
So this is bytes per token
over
DDR bandwidth.
And then this consumes some
amount of the DDR as well.
And every scale-up has DDR and flash?
This is really a deployment
question, so you can choose that.
Nvidia does deploy in this form.
It has both.
Why isn't the cost to retrieve HBM
the bytes divided by memory bandwidth?
It depends what you
define a retrieve to be.
Here, I'm defining retrieve to be,
move it into HBM so that you can
start actually doing inference on it.
Because if it's already in HBM,
you can be doing compute while
you're getting it from HBM to SRAM?
Interesting.
Yeah, for example.
These are three things, and
I guess I ordered them wrong.
In general, if you're balancing
two costs and you've got different
tiers in the memory hierarchy,
you should expect as this cost
goes up, this cost should go down.
You can kind of see where the zeros are.
I should have ordered them this one first,
this one second, and this one third.
If you're going to hold onto it for a
very short amount of time, then all of
this is multiplied by the hold time.
This one is, and so is this
one.
Interestingly, they have
different prices to write for.
Do you specify this in the API
for five minutes versus an hour?
Which suggests that the five
minutes is HBM and the hour is DDR.
I think that's a pretty good assumption.
If you look at the numbers, it might
also turn out that it's one tier
down, and it's DDR versus flash.
Interesting.
I'll look up the price difference.
The base input tokens is
$5 per million tokens.
Base, which means remat.
This is $5.
That's $5
to "retrieve".
And then to write,
presumably HBM, for five minutes is 6.25.
We might be able to determine which
memory tier it is by the durations.
Five minutes versus one hour.
Exactly.
I think this will probably end up being
the drain time of the
memory tier that you're in.
What that means is,
given that I know I'm going
to be holding something for
five minutes, I would like to
pick a memory that I can
read every five minutes.
I can read the whole memory
once per five minutes, ballpark.
That is the drain time of the memory.
So if I take the storage
capacity over storage bandwidth,
I would like this to be
equal to five minutes.
We did this calculation for HBM.
For HBM, we know that this
number is 20 milliseconds.
So HBM is much
too small.
DDR could be about an order of
magnitude or two off from this, so
this is probably on the order of
seconds, like 1 to 10 seconds.
I don't have these numbers memorized,
but generally, as you go to
slower tiers, flash is plausibly
on the order of one minute.
And then spinning disk, which is massively
different, is on the order of one hour.
So this might actually identify the
tiers of flash and spinning disk.
Sorry, why is this the calculation?
This is the storage capacity
divided by the bandwidth?
You've got a bunch of different memory
tiers, we've listed four of them.
Your choice of which memory tier
is about minimizing the cost.
What fraction of the device are you using?
You're using some fraction of the
device for holding onto it, and
then you're using some fraction
of the device to retrieve it.
Let's say I'm using 10% of the device.
And I want to equalize
those two fractions.
That's a sign that I've
hit the right thing.
Let's say I've got some runtime here.
I'm going to hold on for all of this time,
so this is the time-hold.
And then there's going to be some amount
of time here, which is time-retrieve.
Basically to equalize these two
costs, I want the retrieval time
to be equal to the hold time
times the fraction of capacity.
Because this is the retrieval
time, this is how many other
things I can hold simultaneously.
Basically,
you want to store things in there
for so long such that the amount of
time it's in there is the time to
get all your things in there and out.
Yeah basically.
I think that probably indicates that the
two tiers are flash and spinning disk.
I'm kind of shocked to see spinning
disk being used at all, because
it's such an old technology.
Interesting.
It’s also crazy that it’s so
slow that it takes an hour to
load its full capacity to it in.
It’s a really unattractive technology
but it’s useful in some places.
We're sitting down because I
want to ask you some questions
that don't need a blackboard.
You have this extremely interesting
blog post where you talk about how,
at a high level, the architecture
of different cryptographic protocols
looks a lot like neural networks.
There's this convergent evolution
where they both need to jumble
information across all their inputs.
For cryptographic protocols,
it's to make sure that each new
input into a hash function will
totally scramble what happens.
For neural networks, of course, they
need to consider how this piece of
information changes what you should
make of this other piece of information.
I thought that was an
extremely interesting point.
At a high level, in some sense they're
trying to do the inverse thing.
Cryptographic protocols are trying to take
information which has structure and make
it look indistinguishable from randomness.
Neural networks are trying to take
things which look random—protein
sequences, DNA, garbled text—and
extract higher-level structure from it.
They have similar high-level
mechanisms, but they're actually
trying to do the opposite things.
I wonder what you make of that.
I try to look for other examples where
mixing and scrambling shows up as well.
There's almost a physical example
where you're making a cake and
you want to stir the batter.
Literally the idea to first stir
it this way and then stir it this
way is not too bad of an approach.
Beyond that, back to the digital world,
there are some differences,
and the one you call out is
a pretty strong difference.
The way it shows up,
if you just randomly initialize a
neural network, maybe it's a reasonable
cipher as well because the random
initialization is going to jumble
stuff in a complicated way.
It may even do what you want.
Who knows?
The thing that makes it interpretable
is the gradient descent.
You can differentiate a neural network
and get a meaningful derivative.
We do a lot of work to not overcomplicate
the derivative, so the residual
connection keeps it contained and simple.
And so does the LayerNorm
stuff that we do.
One of the biggest attacks against
cryptographic ciphers is also
to differentiate the cipher.
Ciphers
run in a different number field.
They run in the field of two elements,
so just binary, whereas neural nets run,
in theory, in the field of real numbers.
You have to differentiate with
respect to binary numbers, but you
can absolutely differentiate a cipher.
This is called differential cryptanalysis.
Basically, what it says is that if
you take a small difference of the
input, it's quite difficult to make
the difference of the output be small.
The whole job of a well-designed
cipher is to make the
difference in output very large.
The distinction is that the
optimization goals at that
point are about complexifying.
They don't have the same residual
connections, like LayerNorms.
I guess a place where the two merge is
backdoors.
With a backdoor in an LLM, you're
trying to hide… Would you consider it an
input?
It’s not an input into the forward pass
but it’s an input into the backward pass.
You’re trying to hide an
input into the backward pass.
This is an adversarial
context?
This is actually a place where
you get exactly the avalanche
property that ciphers have as well.
Adversarial attacks on image
classification models are about finding
a very small perturbation of the image
that totally changes the classification,
totally changes the output.
That is the common case in
ciphers, whereas that's the
undesired case in neural nets.
Interesting.
Has it at all been a successful field to
actually use neural networks as ciphers?
Almost anything you do in trying to
create a cipher, if it doesn't have 10
years of scrutiny, it's probably broken.
So in that direction,
it's a little dangerous.
In the other direction, there
has been at least one very
clear adoption of technology.
There is a construction where you
take a function, an f[x] function,
which is not invertible, and use
that to build an invertible function.
That started in ciphers.
It's called a Feistel
cipher or Feistel network.
You apply the function f—I want to write
on the blackboard but I won’t—remember
the input, and then you swap the two.
That allows you to
construct invertible layers.
There is a paper from 2018 or 2019
called Reversible Nets, RevNets,
which does exactly this construction.
In addition to your residual
connection, you also remember the
input from the previous layer.
That actually makes the entire
layer reversible and almost
completely eliminates your
memory footprint during training.
Instead of needing to save activations
for the backwards pass, you can
run the entire network backwards
and rematerialize the activations.
Ok, so I was asking you,
have neural networks actually
been used for cryptography?
And we realized it may be better
to just do this on the blackboard.
Are they actually being
used for cryptography?
Using neural nets for cryptography…
In general, creating a new cipher
is a very dangerous proposition.
Almost all of them are broken.
99% of them are broken, so it’s
probably a bad place to start.
But the other direction has
been, in at least one very
clear case, quite productive.
There's a construction
that exists in ciphers and then was
imported into neural nets called a
Feistel cipher, or Feistel network.
The idea is that you may have some
function f which is not invertible,
but you like the function because
it does interesting things, like
it does an MLP, for example.
Or it mixes it in an interesting way.
You'd like to build something
out of this that is invertible.
The construction we're going to make
is going to be a two-input function
rather than a one-input function.
We're
going to apply
f[x].
We need to actually remember what x
was, so we're going to stick x over
here so that we can work backwards,
and then we also can't drop y.
We're going to remember y, and we're going
to add them together to form this tuple.
The way to invert this,
if you think I have
this output and I want to recover
x and y, I can easily recover x.
That's right there, I just read it off.
To recover y, if this thing was called
z, I can recover y by z minus f[x],
because I've already recovered x.
That means this
construction is invertible.
This was used in ciphers
a ton and still is used.
It's one of the main mechanisms
of constructing ciphers.
Often you want ciphers to be invertible,
especially the layers of ciphers, because
that has better cryptographic properties.
This has actually been
ported over
into neural nets.
There's a 2017 paper called
RevNets, reversible networks.
What it does is make the
entire network invertible.
You can apply it to any network,
like a transformer network.
I do a forwards pass, but then I can
run the entire pass backwards as well.
The whole neural network is invertible
with exactly this construction.
This paper applied it to some layer,
like a transformer layer, for example.
We've got this function f,
which is our transformer layer.
Normally we would have just an
input and then a residual connection
coming out, and it gets added
over here.
Now, the variation of this is going
to be we've got two inputs, x and y.
x goes through the
function, gets added to y,
and then this becomes the new x, output x.
Then this x becomes the output y.
Really what this is doing, if
you think of two layers back, is
the thing you mentioned before.
It's doing the residual
connection from two layers back.
This y came from the previous layer
and was the residual connection there.
Because of this construction,
the whole thing is invertible.
Why do I care?
What does invertible matter for?
The big thing that it can be
interesting for is training.
If I think of a forward pass of training…
Let's say I have four layers and I run
them in zero, one, two, three order.
I have to write all of
the activations to HBM.
I get an HBM footprint
here that is kind of linear
in the number of layers.
This can actually be the largest
memory footprint during training.
This is normal training, and then I run
the backwards pass and read it in reverse.
The
forward pass goes forward, and
the backward pass goes backwards.
I have to read them back out.
The idea of this RevNets paper is
that because it's invertible, I
don't need to store this at all.
I can completely rematerialize it.
I run my forwards pass, and then
when I'm running my backwards pass,
I'm simultaneously in lockstep
undoing all of the forwards pass
steps that I did in order to have
the activations that I need here.
This ends up being memory
saving, which is a nice idea.
Interesting.
In some sense you're spending
more compute to save memory.
That's right.
Interesting.
It's the opposite of what
you're doing with the KV cache.
With the KV cache, you're spending
more memory to save compute.
Yeah.
Spending more memory to save
compute is generally profitable
given where hardwares are.
Interesting.
That was super fun.
Reiner, thank you so much for doing it.
I feel like it really
vindicated the vision behind
the studio and the blackboard.
Yeah.
Cool, thanks so much for doing it.
Thanks.